Guide to the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas collection
1901-1987
YCAL MSS 77
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
24
(41 boxes) + 4 art, 4 broadside, 2 cold storage
The Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Collection contains manuscripts, letters, photographs, clippings, artworks, and research materials relating to the life and work of Gertrude Stein and her companion, Alice B. Toklas gathered during the years following Stein's death to supplement the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers (YCAL MSS 76). Items from such friends and admirers as Elizabeth Fuller Chapman, Doda Conrad, Clement Hurd, Samuel Steward, and Donald Sutherland complement the original group of Stein papers. Series I, Writings, includes drafts of works by Stein and several posthumously published items, along with a group of writings by Alice B. Toklas. Series II, Correspondence, contains long runs of letters from Stein to: Edward Aswell, Henry Phelan Gibb, William Garland Rogers, Samuel Steward, Donald Sutherland, and Virgil Thomson, all of which were acquired from the original recipients and several outgoing letters from Gertrude Stein and from Alice Toklas. Series III, Other Papers, contains research materials from Stein scholars, files from the Atlantic Monthly concerning their publication of Stein's work, several musical settings of Stein works, and Doda Conrad's files concerning a fund for Alice Toklas. Series IV and V contain Printed Materials and Series VI contains Photographs, some of Stein and Toklas, but principally of artworks owned by Stein and of posthumous productions of Stein plays. Series VII and VIII (Artworks and Objects), includes a collage painting by Pablo Picasso and a number of paintings by Sir Francis Rose. Series IX, Film and Sound Recordings, contains a film of Stein and Toklas at the Hotel Pernollet in Belley France around 1927 and several audio recordings of Stein readings her works.
Other Storage Formats: Artworks, Objects, Recordings, Oversize
Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
HSR (videocassettes) and motion picture film in cold storage: ‡a Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Artwork in folder 560: Restricted. Item is on permanent loan to the Yale University Art Gallery. For more information please consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Collection was acquired through gifts and purchases from various sources, in many cases friends and contemporaries of Stein and Toklas, to complement the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers (YCAL MSS 76).
GERTRUDE STEIN (1874-1946) AND ALICE B. TOKLAS (1877-1967)
A biographical timeline is provided in the register for the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers (YCAL MSS 76).
Associated Materials
In years past, A number of items by or relating to Stein in other collections held by the library were interfiled into the Gertrude Stein Collection to facilitate research In the course of processing, these have been returned to their collections of origin. For example, letters from Alice Toklas to Pavel Tchelitchew have been returned to the Tchelitchew Papers, a separate group of material in the Yale Collection of American Literature. Repatriated material once filed with the Stein/Toklas Collection can be found in the papers of:
Isabel Wilder
Henry McBride
Robert Haas
To research Stein material in these collections, please consult the catalogs (for both printed and manuscript material) and finding aids for archival material. In addition to the items listed under Series IX, Film & Sound Recordings, there are two items that were purchased by the Historical Sound Recordings department which may have mistakenly been cited by researchers in the past as being part of the Stein Collection. These are:
"Gertrude Stein Reads" containing the Making of Americans Parts 1 & 2, A Valentine to Sherwood Anderson, If I told him, Matisse [alternate recording], and Madame Recamier. (One double-sided 12" 33-1/3 RPM disc. Pressed by Caedmon in 1956.) and "Spoken Arts Treasury of 100 Modern American Poets" vol. 1. Includes Stein reading: She bowed to her brother, Georges Hugnet, Fifteenth of November, and Portrait of Christian Bérard. (One double-sided 12" 33-1/3 RPM disc. Pressed by Spoken Arts.)
See also: The Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Papers (YCAL MSS 76) and the Leo Stein Collection (YCAL MSS 78).
Scope and Contents
The Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Collection consists of manuscripts, letters, photographs, printed materials, and art and objects by and about Stein and Toklas. The Collection spans the years 1901-1987.
The Collection is housed in 39 boxes and consists of nine series: Writings, Correspondence, Other Papers, Photographs, Pre-1946 Printed Material, Post-1946 Printed Material, Artworks, Objects, and Film & Sound Recordings. Boxes 37-40 contain Oversize material.
Series I, Writings, consists of three subseries: Gertrude Stein Bibliography, Posthumous Appearances of Stein Works, and Writings of Alice B. Toklas. The Gertrude Stein Bibliography contains several holograph and typescript versions of published Stein writings, most of which are copies that Stein sent to friends. Also present are materials used in the publication of Stein's works, such as the page proof for the Banyan Press edition of Blood on the Dining Room Floor, the setting typescript for Brewsie and Willie, the setting typescripts and proof pages for Last Operas and Plays and Selected Writings, both published posthumously, and the page proofs for the original edition of Operas and Plays, with corrections by Stein. A nearly complete history of two editions of The World is Round can be found here, each of them including original illustrations by Clement Hurd.
Posthumous Appearances of Stein Works contains printed items in magazines and reviews collected by the library. Writings of Alice B. Toklas consists chiefly of printed versions of excerpts from two of her books and of several articles written during the 1950s. What is Remembered is present in a proof stage.
Series II, Correspondence, is divided into four subseries: Gertrude Stein - Outgoing, Gertrude Stein - Incoming, Alice B. Toklas - Outgoing, and Third-Party. Letters from Gertrude Stein (Gertrude Stein - Outgoing) comprise the largest group. Donated in most cases by the recipient, these groups of letters complement many of those found in the Stein/Toklas Papers. An extensive group of letters to Virgil Thomson makes up much of this sub-series. In addition, there are substantial runs of letters to Edward Aswell, William Cook, Max Ewing, Henry Phelan Gibb, Bobsy Chapman, Lindley Williams Hubbell, Grant Richards, William Garland Rogers, William P. Sears, Jr., Julian and Rosellen Stein, Samuel Steward, Donald Sutherland, Ellen Alix Taylor, Mabel Foote Weeks, and Wendell Wilcox. A few letters to Stein, which somehow were passed along to other parties, are to be found in the subseries: Gertrude Stein - Incoming.
The subseries Alice B. Toklas - Outgoing is made up of letters by Alice Toklas written to a variety of friends during the two decades following Gertrude Stein's death. Her notes to old and young correspondents record her trials and triumphs as she continued to work on Gertrude's behalf. Third-Party Letters, which close out this series, for the most part document the publication of works by or about Gertrude Stein.
Series III, Other Papers, includes several reminiscences of Gertrude and Alice, by Arthur Lachman, by William Garland Rogers, and by Dilkusha Rohan, musical settings of Stein (or Stein-inspired) works by Richard Banks, by Johnny Fig, and by Ned Rorem, and working notes for books, plays and documentaries about Stein, by such writers and artists as Perry Miller Adato, Nancy Cole, Ulla Dydo, Linda Simon, and Elizabeth Sprigge. Among the most extensive holdings in this series are three unique groups of material. The editorial office files from the Atlantic Monthly from 1919-1942 include letters from and to Stein and copies of several of her submissions. This is the one instance in both the Collection and the Papers (besides the appearance of a few proof states of manuscripts) of a publisher's archive of Stein material. Letters and documents gathered by Doda Conrad describe his somewhat successful efforts to establish a living trust fund for the welfare of Alice Toklas as she became enfeebled in the mid-1960s. Researchers interested in Stein's texts will find the transcriptions made by Leon Katz of Stein's studies for the Making of Americans (originals located in the Stein papers) with explanatory notes by Katz.
Series IV, Photographs, contains a number of snapshots of Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas, photos of artwork owned by Stein of Stein exhibitions, and a number of shots taken during the 1940s and 1950s of stage productions of Stein plays.
Series V and VI gather together all of the miscellaneous printed material about Stein acquired by the library during the decades following her death. The material in Series V, Pre-1946 Printed Material, contains ephemera given to Stein. Series VI, Post-1946 Printed Material, gathers together items which document the fortunes of Stein's friends and the appearances of her posthumous writings. A few items in this series, do, indeed, date from before 1946. However, these tend to be clippings that were received from third parties in groups of principally post-1946 material. The three boxes containing issues of magazines and printed items with mentions of Gertrude Stein are arranged in alphabetical order by name of publication.
Series VII, Artworks, and Series VIII, Objects, consist of paintings, sketches, and memorabilia given by friends and admirers of Stein and Toklas. These include several items by Sir Francis Rose, an oil painting by Camille Lane, and a mixed media painting by Pablo Picasso.
Series IX, Film & Sound Recordings, contains one film taken by Julian Stein in approximately 1927 showing Gertrude and Alice at the Hotel Pernollet in Belley, France, as well as views of Michael Stein's home. The sound recordings include an interview with and readings by Stein recorded during her American tour in 1934-35. (Use copies for all the sound recordings are available at the Historical Sound Recordings department of Sterling Library.)
Reference prints for artworks and objects in box 36 have been made to facilitate access to images of these materials.
The oversize section contains items cross-referenced from series I, III, IV, and VI. Oversize artworks and objects have been provided with appropriate housing, as indicated in Series VII and VIII.
Atlantic monthly (Boston, Mass.: 1857); American literature -- 20th Century; Americans -- France -- History -- 20th Century; Art and literature; Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Cubism and literature; Literature, Experimental; Modernism (Art); Modernism (Literature); Women authors, American -- 20th Century; Paris (France) -- Intellectual life; Motion pictures (visual works); Paintings (visual works); Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Authors; Aswell, Edward C. (Edward Campbell), 1900-1958; Banks, R. R. (Richard R.); Berman, Eugene, 1899-1972; Burns, Edward; Buss, Kate; Campbell, Sandy; Chapman, Elizabeth Fuller; Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1882-1966; Cone, Etta, 1870-1949; Conrad, Doda; Dydo, Ulla E., 1925-; Ewing, Max; Fourcade, Xavier; Gibb, Henry Phelan; Grosser, Maurice, 1903-1986; Harrison, Gilbert A.; Hurd, Clement, 1908-1988; Johnson, Lamont; Knapik, Harold, 1916-1976; Levy, Harriet Lane; Lutz, Mark, 1901-1969; Merrill, James, 1926-1995; Padgette, Paul; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973; Richards, Grant, 1872-1948; Rogers, W. G. (William Garland), 1896-1978; Rose, Francis, Sir, 1909-1979; Sears, William Paul, 1902-; Simon, Linda, 1946-; Sprigge, Elizabeth, 1900-1974; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Steward, Samuel M., 1909-1993; Sutherland, Donald, 1915-1978; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-1989; Toklas, Alice B., 1877-1967; Wilcox, Wendell; Windham, Donald
- Writings, 1910-1985; Series I; 3; (8 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Writings, is organized into three sections, each of which are arranged alphabetically by title of writing.
  - GERTRUDE STEIN BIBLIOGRAPHY
    - And so. To change so
      - Typescript, [1924] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - A Ballad
      - Holograph MS, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Inscribed to Frank Gervasi [1944?] Sep
    - La Baronne Pierlot
      - Typescript, n.d.
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Series II, Correspondence, GERTRUDE STEIN - OUTGOING, William Garland Rogers, Box 10, folder 142
    - Blood on the Dining Room Floor
      - Page proof (1st gathering) for Banyan Press edition, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Unbound set of signatures for Banyan Press edition, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brewsie and Willie
      - Setting typescript of American edition, corrected (with cover page from plate proof), 1946 Jan (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Adaptation by Jean Cluff for the Columbia Workshop, typescript mimeograph, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Adaptation by Ellen Violett and Lisabeth Blake "for Touring Players, Inc.," typescript carbon, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Adaptation by Ellen Violett: "Touring Players, Inc. Television Adaptation" typescript, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Capital Capitals
      - Mimeograph copy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cezanne
      - Typescript carbon, 1927
        See: Series III, Other Papers - ATLANTIC MONTHLY FILES, Box 15, folder 246
    - Composition as Explanation
      - First proof for Hogarth Press edition, corrected, 1926 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Four Proteges
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Four Saints in Three Acts
      - Typescript carbon, [1934] (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Program: Hartford premiere, annotated with clippings, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Program: New York City, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Advertising flyer with article by Stark Young, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Accompanied by clipping for 1934 and 1952 productions
    - France and the Eiffel Tower
      - Holograph MS, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Frost
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Geography and Plays
      - Order form, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Hail and Farewell!
      - Typescript, corrected, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Harold Loeb
      - Holograph MS (in hand of ABT) (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Inscribed to HL by GS
    - Harriet [Making Plans]
      - Typescript, corrected, [1910] (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Introduction to Francis Rose
      - Printed version with exhibition catalog, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Signed by Gertrude Stein
    - Ireland
      - Typescript carbon, 1919
        See: Series III, Other Papers - ATLANTIC MONTHLY FILES, Box 15, folder 245
    - Keys to a Closet [and] A Book...
      [full titles: Keys to a Closet [and] A Book concluding with as a wife has a cow]
      - Page proofs, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Last Operas and Plays
      - Setting typescript, corrected by Jeanette Fellheimer, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 24-29)
        Includes corrected pages from 1932 editions of Operas and Plays
      - Galley proof, corrected by Carl Van Vechten and William Raney, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Letter to Rousseau Voorhies
      - Printed version, Chicago Sunday Magazine of Books, with letter from Norman Holmes Pearson to "Gilbert", 1946 Sep 8
        See: Oversize, Box 37, folder 579
    - Life and Death of Juan Gris
      - Printed version: exhibition catalog, Paris, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Madame de Clermont-Tonnerre
      - Holograph MS, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
        In hand of ABT and GS
    - Mi-careme
      - Typescript copy, corrected, [1912] (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Miss Furr and Miss Skeene
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Mrs. Reynolds
      - Holograph fragment
        See: Series II, Correspondence, GERTRUDE STEIN - OUTGOING, Julian Sawyer, Box 10, folder 147
    - Monsieur Vollard et Cezanne
      - Typescript carbon copy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Moral Tales of 1920 and 1921
      - Typescript, n.d.
        See: Series II, Correspondence - THIRD-PARTY - Eugene P. Ullman, Box 14, folder 240
    - The Mother of Us All
      - Order form for Music Press edition, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Nadelman
      - Typescript carbon copy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Operas and Plays
      - First and second page proofs, corrected by GS and signed by Maurice Darantiere, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 38-40)
        See also: Last Operas and Plays, Box 2, folder 24
    - Picasso
      - Advertisement and order form (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - The Revery of the Zionist
      - Typescript carbon, 1919
    - Selected Writings
      - Printer's setting copy, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 42-47)
      - Galley proof, corrected, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - Page proofs, corrected, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - Plate proofs, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Things As They Are
      - Unbound set of signatures for Banyan Press edition, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - To do: Alphabets and Birthdays
      - Typescript copy, corrected [incomplete], n.d. (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - To Kitty or Kate Buss
      - Typescript, n.d.
        See: Series II, Correspondence, GERTRUDE STEIN - OUTGOING, Kate Buss, Box 9, folder 104
    - Two Women
      - Typescript carbon copy, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - What Are Masterpieces
      - Advertising flyer, [1940] (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - What Does She See When She Shuts Her Eyes
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d.
        See: Series III, Other Papers - ATLANTIC MONTHLY FILES, Box 15, folder 249
    - Why I Like Detective Stories
      - Printed version, Harper's Bazaar, 1937 Nov
        See: Series II, Correspondence, GERTRUDE STEIN - OUTGOING, Samuel Steward, Box 11, folder 155
    - William P. Sears, Jr.
      - Holograph manuscript
        See: Series II, Correspondence, GERTRUDE STEIN - OUTGOING, William P. Sears, Jr., Box 10, folder 149
    - The World is Round
      - Typescript, corrected, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 55)
        Includes letter from the Baroness D'Aiguy to William R. Scott, Inc., 1939 May 22, and photograph of Rose D'Aiguy
      - W.R. Scott edition, 1939
        Illustrated by Clement Hurd
        - Page proofs (text only), incomplete, [1939] (Box 6, Folder 56)
        - Layout dummy for illustrations with proof of text pasted on, [1939] (Box 6, Folder 57)
        - Pencil sketches for advertising material, [1939] (Box 6, Folder 58)
        - Rough pencil sketches for illustrations, [1939] (Box 6, Folder 59)
        - Tempera drafts of illustrations with page numbers, [1939] (Box 6, Folder 60-61)
        - Tempera drafts of illustrations for chapter divisions marked "Sketches sent to Miss Stein", [1939] (Box 6, Folder 62-63)
        - Final tempera illustrations, [1939] (Box 6, Folder 64-68)
        - Color page proof of illustrations: pages 4, 23, and 33, [1939] (Box 6, Folder 69)
        - Advertising flyer, [1939] (Box 6, Folder 70)
      - Young Scott Books edition, 1966
        - Layout dummy for illustrations with text pasted on (one page), [ca. 1964] (Box 6, Folder 71)
        - Galley proof (one page), 1964 Oct 14 (Box 6, Folder 72)
        - Rough pencil sketches for illustrations, [ca. 1964]
          See: Oversize, Box 37, folders 580-582
        - Linoleum print drafts of illustrations, [ca. 1964]
          See: Oversize, Box 37, folders 583-609
        - Final linoleum color studies and separations, [ca. 1964]
          See: Oversize, Box 38, folders 610-633
    - Yes is For a Very Young Man
      - Typescript, corrected [by Alice Toklas?] of earlier version entitled "In Savoie"/ "In Savoy", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 73)
      - Typescript and carbon, corrected by GS (Box 6, Folder 74)
      - Typescript carbon copy, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 75)
      - Program for production at Pasadena Playhouse, 1946 Mar 13 (Box 6, Folder 76)
      - Mimeograph script for Biarritz American University production, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - POSTHUMOUS APPEARANCES OF STEIN WORKS
    - Everybody's Autobiography
      - Excerpt concerning A Wedding Bouquet, printed version, About the House, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - From Dark to Day
      - French translation (as "Des jours sombres aux jours de lumière"), printed version, Le Promeneur, 1985 Dec (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - How Could They Marry Her
      - Printed version, Envoy, 1951 Jan (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - I Like American and American
      - Printed version, '47, 1947 Oct (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Introduction to Elie Lascaux
      - Printed version, exhibition catalog, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Introduction to Francis Rose
      - Printed version, exhibition catalog, New York City, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Is Dead
      - Printed version, Occident, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Ladies' Voices
      - French translation (as "Voix des Femmes"), printed version, in'hui, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Lipschitz [and] Francis Picabia
      - French translations, printed version, Art Press, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - A Patriotic Leading
      - Printed version, Time, 1946 Nov 11 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Raoul Dufy
      - Offprint from Les Arts Plastique, [1949] (Box 7, Folder 88)
        Inscribed from Alice Toklas to Carl Van Vechten
      - Printed version, Les Arts Plastique, 1949 Nov (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Reflections on the Atomic Bomb
      [with Sonnets That Please (IV)]
      - Printed versions, Yale Poetry Review, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Rich and Poor in English
      - Printed version with parallel French translation, Le Nouveau Commerce, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Sonnets That Please (IV)
      See: Reflections on the Atomic Bomb, Box 7, folder 89
      - Box 7, folder 89
  - WRITINGS OF ALICE B. TOKLAS
    - The Alice B. Toklas Cookbook
      - Printed excerpt entitled "Secrets of French Cooking," House Beautiful, 1954 Nov (Box 8, Folder 92)
    - Fifty Years of French Fashion
      - Printed version, Atlantic, 1958 Jun (Box 8, Folder 93)
    - Food, Artists, and the Baroness
      - Printed version, Vogue, 1950 Mar 1 (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - Quartre Saints en Trois Actes, [memoir]
      - Printed version, Preuves, 1952 May (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Staying on Alone
      - Advance publicity package of nine letters by ABT, photocopy, [1973] (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - They Who Came to Paris
      - Printed version, New York Times Book Review, 1950 Aug 6 (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - What is Remembered
      - Uncorrected proofs, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 98)
      - Printed excerpt entitled "Brilliant Wonderland of Alice B. Toklas," Life International, 1963 Mar 25
        See: Oversize, Box 38, folder 634
- Correspondence, 1901-1977; Series II; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Series II, Correspondence, is organized into four sections, which are arranged alphabetically.
  - GERTRUDE STEIN - OUTGOING
    - Abdy, Robert and Diana, 1936, 1938, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 99)
      Includes one letter from ABT and explanatory note from Ulla Dydo
    - Aswell, Edward, 1933-37 (Box 9, Folder 100)
      Includes typescript of letter from EA to GS, 1933
    - Benno, Benjamin, [1937-38] (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Bradley, William, 1931-32 (Box 9, Folder 102)
      Includes typescript copy of telegram from WB to GS
    - Brewer, Joseph, [1928, 1935?] (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - Buss, Kate, [1933, 1937, n.d.] (Box 9, Folder 104)
      Includes typescript carbon of To Kitty or Kate Buss
    - Cerf, Bennett, [1941] (Box 9, Folder 105)
      Includes letter from BC to Harrison Steeves, 1941 Jul 3, forwarding the letter from GS
    - Chapman, Elizabeth Fuller ("Bobsy"), 1934-46 (Box 9, Folder 106-110)